Guide to the Gladys Adelina Lewis papers, 1909-1975
Lewis, Gladys Adelina papers, 1990-1975
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Gladys Adelina Lewis papers, 1909-1975
7763
Gladys Adelina. Lewis
5.9 cubic feet.
Manuscripts
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Manuscripts, correspondence, and other materials of early 20th century writer Gladys Adelina Lewis.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Gladys Adelina Lewis was born in Los Angeles on May 23, 1891 and died in 1975 in San Francisco. She was a writer and forceful personality who lived in Paris, New York, San Francisco, Hollywood, and Portland, Oregon, moving in artistic and queer circles in the first half of the twentieth century. The child of a prominent Los Angeles family, Lewis was the guinea pig for her mother Selma's experimental and, at the time, well-publicized child-rearing methods, which included mandatory reading of Byron, vigorous exercise, and a stringent diet. Lewis published a poem in a local Los Angeles newspaper at age nine, and at thirteen a poem she wrote attracted the attention of American poet Ella Wheeler Wilcox. From that early age she went on to write fiction, poetry, musicals, and film scripts, using the pseudonyms Georges Lewys and Serge G. Wolsey. Lewis achieved notoriety with The Temple of Pallas-Athenae (which she claimed to have written at age nineteen), a defense of eugenics which violated contemporary obscenity laws and was subsequently banned from the mails. Call House Madam (1942), a fictionalized tell-all of Hollywood madam Lee Francis, suffered the same fate, but was reprinted and reissued numberous times for 20 years. Lewis' collection of poetry, The Epic of Verdun and Ballads of France, was enshrined with great pomp and ceremony in the war monument at Verdun in 1931, a publicity stunt that Lewis herself masterminded.
Lewis was a prolific writer and a shameless self-promoter. She honored libraries world-wide with presentation copies of her books; her correspondence includes letters showing that she nominated herself for the Nobel Prize; she was given the Key to the City of San Francisco in 1935; she adored photographic portraits of herself; she embellished; and she died in obscurity. In life, she was best known for frank works that sorely tried American attitudes about sex, and for a litigious streak that frequently placed her in court, most notably on the losing end of a $1,250,000 plagarism lawsuit against Eugene O'Neill. In numberous interviews included in the collection, Lewis refers to herself as a classicist, but the breadth of her work reveals a truly multi-faceted artist, with early poetry published in Pagan magazine demonstrating a deciededly modern and experimental slant. Additionally, Lewis was a patriot, and staunch defender of Allied forces; there are many rousing war poems in her early work. As much interested in monetary gain and fame as she was in literary virtuosity, Lewis' archive includes drafts for scores of films and plays intended to appeal to the masses, many of them rendered not saleable by racy content. Later work documents Lewis' exploration of gender role reversals and the sexual subculture of the 1940s and 1950s. A self-identified lesbian, at least in later life, Lewis' papers provide valuable insight to the large but mostly invisible queer community of the straitlaced post-war years, and her writings on the psychoanalytic theories of the day serve to illuminate some of the birth pains of that system of ideas.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Drafts and revisions of works published and unpublished, correspondence, and contractual material relating to Lewis' many and various pursuits (as a publisher, an impresario, and the president of the Freudian Society). There is also printed materal--her own self-published works, articles on lawsuits in which she appeared, interviews, and reviews of her work. Also included are a number of photographs, copperplate engravings with designs for the jacket of Call House Madam, other stamps, a "Key to San Francisco", and her business or "calling" cards.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Lewis, Gladys Adelina.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Manuscripts
About Gladys Adelina Lewis' Work
Box 1
Adelina Patti: Her Life, Loves, and Letters
Box 1, 4
Big Doll
Box 1
Call House Madam
Box 1, 4, 6, 7
Cerebral Love
Box 1
The Charmed American
Box 2, 4
"Don Juan of the Rose"
Box 2
The Epic of Verdun and Ballads
Box 2, 4, 5
Every Woman Does
Box 2
Gay People
Box 2
The House of Love
Box 2, 4
Kings and Courtesans
Box 2, 3, 6
Love Sonnets
Box 3
Merry-Go-Round
Box 3, 4
"Mexicali"
Box 3
The Temple of Pallas-Athenae
Box 3, 4
A Woman of Fifty
Box 3
Unpublished and Minor Works
Box 3, 4
Series II. Correspondence
Box 4
Series III. Organizations
The Martin Tudordale Corporation
Box 5
The Freudian Foundation
Box 5
Lavater-Dorette
Box 5
Dramatists Guild of the Authors League of America
Box 5
Series IV. Photographs
Box 5, 8
Series V. Ephemera
Box 5, 6
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Manuscripts
  - About Gladys Adelina Lewis' Work (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Adelina Patti: Her Life, Loves and Letters
    - Bound Manuscript (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Notes (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Letters of Adelina Patti (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Drafts of Short Pieces, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "The Kiss Waltz" Script (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
    - "Lavara y Patti: Sunrise on the Moon" Screen Treatment (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Publicity and Newsclippings, 1943-1967 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Big Doll
    - Manuscripts (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
    - Two Summaries (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Two 34 Page Manuscripts (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Call House Madam
    - Bound Manscripts, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 13-14)
    - Draft, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Revisions: Two Incomplete Drafts (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Notes (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Synopsis for Motion Picture (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - "The Madam: A Musical Comedy" (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Publishing Numbers and Bills (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Rights and Contracts (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Obscenity Case (Box 1, Folder 22-23)
    - Publicity and Newsclippings, 1943-1962 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Paperback Copy of Call House Madam, 1963 (Box 6)
    - Scrap Book, 1928-1960 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Copperplate Engravings (Designs for Call House Madam book jacket) (Box 7)
  - Cerebral Love
    - Manuscripts (Box 1, Folder 24-25)
  - The Charmed American
    - Bound Manuscripts (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Legal Agreements (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Publicity (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - "Don Juan of the Rose"
    - Notes and Manuscript (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - The Epic of Verdun and Ballads
    - Bound Manuscript (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Tipped-In Material (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Notes (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Legal Agreements (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Postcards (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Publicity and Newsclippings, 1918-1963 (Box 4, Folder 8-9)
    - Verdun Brochures and Monument Ceremony, 1920-1930 (Box 4, Folder 10-11)
    - Published Copies (Box 5)
  - Every Woman Does: The Story of a Social Lion Who Came out of the West
    - Bound Manuscripts (Box 2, Folder 9-10)
    - Notes and Synopses for Motion Picture (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Gay People
    - Manuscript (Box 2, Folder 12-14)
    - Early Draft (Box 2, Folder 15-16)
    - Early Draft, Possibly the First (Box 2, Folder 17-18)
    - Prologue Drafts (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Revisions (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Notes and Material (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - The House of Love
    - Bound Manuscript, 1919 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Tipped-In Material (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Frontispiece Illustration, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Screen and Dramatic Treatments, 1935-1962 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Publicity, 1927-1935 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Kings and Courtesans, or The American Noblesse. A Political Opera-Bouffe in a Prologue and Three Acts
    - Bound Manuscripts, 1925 (Box 2, Folder 26-27)
    - Notes (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Piano Score (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Copyright Documents, 1910-1951 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Love Sonnets
    - Bound Manuscript, 1928 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Manuscripts, 1929 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Merry-Go-Round
    - Synopses for Stage and Screen (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Copyright and Legal Agreements, 1923-1939 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Publicity and Newsclippings (Box 4, Folder 13-14)
  - "Mexicali: A Musical Melodrama by Georges Lewys"
    Also titled: "Caliente," "A Lark at the Owl," and "Ensenada"
    - Manuscript (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Synopses for Stage and Screen (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - The Temple of Pallas-Athenae (Posterite)
    - Bound Manuscript, 1929 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Notes (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Synopses for Stage and Screen (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Copyright and Legal Notes, 1924-1951 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Publicity and Newsclippings, 1924-1934 (Box 4, Folder 15-18)
  - A Woman of Fifty
    Also titled: A Courtesan of France
    - Bound Manuscript (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Manuscript, 1928 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Manuscripts and Inspirational Newsclippings (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Unpublished and Minor Works
    - Short Stories (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Essays (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Screenplays and Dramas, 1911-1946 (Box 3, Folder 18-20)
      - "The Jewels of Gonave" (Box 3, Folder 21)
      - "Kitty, I'll Get You That!" (Box 3, Folder 22-23)
      - "Love Dream" (Box 3, Folder 24)
      - "Romance in Geneva", ca. 1938 (Box 3, Folder 25-26)
      - "The Tiger-Lily", ca. 1913 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Publicity and Newsclippings, 1914-1963 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Brochures and Advertisements (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - How to Fly by Gordon E. Revley, Arranged by Glad Lewis, 1917 (Box 5)
    - A Pagan Anthology (Box 6)
    - Poetry and Lyrics (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Musical Scores (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Notes and Fragments (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Copyrights and Legal Agreements, 1910-1972 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Series II. Correspondence
  - Personal Correspondence, 1906-1966 (Box 4, Folder 20-24)
    Arranged Chronologically
  - Adelina Patti, 1919-1953 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Call House Madam, 1942-1977 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - The Charmed American, 1918-1925 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - The Epic of Verdun and Ballads
    - Letters of Appreciation, 1924-1936 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Letters of Appreciation (Copies), 1925-1936 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Arrangements for Monument Ceremony, 1927-1929 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Iron Division, 1922-1931 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Letters to and from Universities and Libraries (United States of America), 1924-1958 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Letters to and from Universities and Libraries ("Foreign"), 1928-1958 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Letters to and from Mussolini and Advisors, Regarding an Italian War Epic, 1931-1934 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Merry-Go-Round, 1924-1930 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - The Temple of Pallas-Athenae (Posterite), 1923-1928 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Mexicali: A Musical Melodrama by Georges Lewys, 1926-1927 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Unpublished and Minor Works, 1909-1945 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Fred de Gresac Estate, 1943-1975 (Box 4, Folder 39-40)
- III. Organizations
  Gladys Lewis was the President of the Martin Tudordale Corporation; a founding member of the Freudian Foundation; and her mother and brother, Selma and Paul Lewis, had a stake in Lavater-Dorette.
  - The Martin Tudordale Corporation
    - Papers, 1944-1969 (Box 5, Folder 1-3)
    - Martin Tudordale Corporation Seal (Box 5)
  - The Freudian Foundation, 1934-1947 (Box 5, Folder 4-6)
  - Lavater-Dorette, 1925-1930 (Box 5, Folder 7-8)
  - Dramatists Guild of the Authors League of America, 1936-1950 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- IV. Photographs
  - Gladys Adelina Lewis
    - Gladys Adelina Lewis (Box 5, Folder 10-11)
    - Oversized Photographs of Gladys Adelina Lewis (and one of Ted Shaw) (Box 8)
  - Friends and Acquaintances (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Lewis' Work (Box 5, Folder 13)
- V. Ephemera
  - Calling Cards (Box 5)
  - "Reading" Stamp (Box 5)
  - Key to San Francisco (Box 6)
SEPARATED MATERIAL
The following materials have been separated from the collection. Some may have been cataloged individually:
Baldwin, James. Giovanni's Room. New York: Dell Publishing Company, 1964, c1956. HSX PS3552.A365 G48 1964
Bannon, Ann. I Am a Woman. New York: Fawcett Publications, [1959]. First Printing, January 1959. HSX PS3552.A615 I2 c.2
_________. Odd Girl Out. Greenwich, Connecticut: Fawcett Publications, 1960, c1957. (duplicate copy already in HSX)
Lawrence, D.H. Lady Chatterley's Lover. New York: Signet, c1962, 20th printing, 1963. HSX PR6023.A96 L1 1963
Rossiter, F.M. The Torch of Life: A Key to Sex Harmony. New York: Eugenics Publishing Company, c1939. HSX HQ31.R83 1939